Pengyu Cheng □ pengyu.cheng@duke.edu • • linear95.github.io

Research Interests

I am a Ph.D. student at Duke University. My research interests focus on Bayesian deep learning, geometric deep learning, and their applications in natural language processing. Currently, I am working on disentangled text generation and time-evolving graph generation.

Education

Duke University 08/2017–Present

Ph.D. Student, Electrical and Computer Engineering

Tsinghua University 08/2013–07/2017

B.S., Mathematics and Statistics

Experience

Information Initiative at Duke (iiD)

08/2017-Present

Research Assistant Adviser: Lawrence Carin

Bayesian deep learning, geometric deep learning, and their applications in natural language processing.

NEC Laboratories America, Inc. 05/2019–08/2019

Research Internship Adviser: Martin Rengiang Min

Disentangled text generation learning from an information-theoretic perspective.

Tsinghua Intelligent Vision Group (IVG)

03/2016-07/2016

Student Researcher Adviser: Jiwen Lu

Deep metric learning for person re-identification based on sequential frames information.

Student Research Program at Tsinghua

11/2015-05/2017

Student Researcher Adviser: Xuegong Zhang

Non-parametric k-sample tests with statistics based on local maximum energy distance.

Beijing Sogou Information Service Co., Ltd.

08/2014-09/2014

Research Internship Mentor: Mao Wang

Polygonal line-like city road data smoothing via Spline Interpolation; road data compressing via Douglas-Peucker algorithm.

Publications

- o **P. Cheng**, Y. Li, X. Zhang, L. Chen, D. Carlson, L. Carin, "Dynamic Embedding on Textual Networks via a Gaussian Process", Under Review Submission to AAAI 2020
- P. Cheng *, D. Shen *, D. Sundararaman, X. Zhang, Q. Yang, M. Tang, A. Celikyilmaz, and L. Carin, "Learning Compressed Sentence Representations for On-Device Text Processing", Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), 2019 Oral
- P. Cheng, Y. Li, X. Zhang, L. Chen, D. Carlson, L. Carin, "Gaussian-Process-Based Dynamic Embedding for Textual Networks", Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Workshop, 2019
- L. Chen, G. Wang, C. Tao, D. Shen, P. Cheng, X. Zhang, W. Wang, Y. Zhang, and L. Carin, "Improving Textual Network Embedding with Global Attention via Optimal Transport", Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), 2019
- o C. Liu, J. Zhuo, **P. Cheng**, R. Zhang, J. Zhu, and L. Carin, "Understand and Accelerate Particle-based Variational Inference", International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2019
- o **P. Cheng**, C. Liu, C. Li, D. Shen, H. Ricardo, and L. Carin, "Straight-Through Estimator as Projected Wasserstein Gradient Flow", Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Workshop, 2018 Spotlight

Academic Activities

o Conference reviewer/PC member for AAAI 2020	09/2019
o Teaching assistant for <i>Introduction to Deep Learning</i> , Instructor: Vahid Tarokh, Ph.D.	09/2019
o Oral Presentation at ACL 2019	07/2019
o Spotlight talk at NeurIPS 2019 Bayesian Deep Learning workshop	12/2018
Awards	
o Fellowship of Electrical and Computer Engineering at Duke	08/2017

o Academic Excellence Award of Tsinghua University (top 30%)	10/2014
o Top 5 in the 18-th "Sogou Cup" Artificial Intelligence Programming Contest (5/200)	04/2014
o Silver medal in the 28-th Chinese Mathematical Olympiad (CMO)	01/2013

Technical Strengths

Computer Languages: Python (Tensorflow, Pytorch), R, C/C++

o First in Duke-Tsinghua Machine Learning Summer School (1/112)

Software & Tools: LaTeX, Emacs, Mathematica, MATLAB, Excel, Markdown

o First Prize in Chinese National Olympiad in Informatics in Provinces (NOIP)

Graduate Courses

Theoretical: Random Signals and Noise; Information Theory; Multivariate Statistical Analysis; Stochastic Processes; Compressed Sensing;

Engineering: Programming, Data Structure and Algorithms in C++; Pattern Recognition; Machine Learning; Text Data Analysis;

08/2017

11/2012